# **LU YIN**

Email: yinluu.cn@gmail.com Webpage: https://luuyin.com

Google Scholar: <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=G4Xe1NkAAAAJ">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=G4Xe1NkAAAAJ</a>

## **ABOUT ME**

Hi, I'm Lu, an Assistant Professor at the **University of Aberdeen** and a long-term Visiting Researcher at **Eindhoven University of Technology**. My primary research mainly focus is on **enhancing the Efficiency and Scalability of AI models**. I believe that passion and persistence are the keystones of groundbreaking research, and I am committed to delivering research of unparalleled quality.

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

# AI Efficientcy

# LLM

# Computer Vision

# ML/DL

# AI Interdisciplinary Applications

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

University of Aberdeen

#### **Assistant Professor**

- Teach and Mentor Master/Ph.D. students.
- · Secure grants.
- Research area: Al Efficiency, Al for Science, Large Language Models

Google, New York Office 07/2023 – 09/2023

# Al Researcher (Intern)

• Build efficient large language models (LLM)

Eindhoven University of Technology 07/2023 - 11/2023

# Postdoctoral Researcher

- Mentor Master/Ph.D. students.
- Publish research findings.

#### **EDUCATION**

Eindhoven University of Technology 10/2018 - 2/2023

## Ph.D in Computer Science

**Department**: Mathematics and Computer Science

Specialization: Knowledge Elicitation, Data Efficiency, Model Efficiency

Promotors: Prof. Dr. Mykola Pechenizkiy; Dr. Vlado Menkovski

Harbin Institute of Technology (Shenzhen)

09/2015 - 07/2018

## Master in Control Engineering

**Department**: Mechanical Engineering and Automation

Specialization: Computer Vision, Robotics

Promotors: Prof. Dr.Xiaorui Zhu

Harbin Institute of Technology 09/2009 - 07/2013

**Bachelor in Electrical Engineering and Automation** 

**Department**: Information and Electrical Engineering

#### AWARDS AND HONOURS

- 12/2022 Best Paper Award at Learning on Graphs Conference (LoG). 2022.
- 06/2017 Best Paper Nomination Award at International Conference on Computer Vision Systems (ICVS), 2017

## GRANT

## high-performance computing grant

• 2022 EINF-2694: HPC Cloud (CPU): 50.000 hr,

HPC Cloud (GPU: NVIDIA GeForce RTX 2080 Ti): 10,000 hr

- 2022 EINF-2943: NVIDIA A100, 1,000,000 Credits (7,812 hr)
- 2023 EINF-5205: HPC Cloud (GPU: NVIDIA GeForce RTX 2080 Ti): 10,000 hr
- 2023 EINF-5206: NVIDIA A100, 1,000,000 Credits (7,812 hr)
- 2023 NWO-2023.027/L1: NVIDIA A100, 10,000,000 Credits (78,120 hr)

## RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

#### Talks:

- Going beyond training ML models with labels at EDGE AI, Eindhoven University of Technology, 2020
- Model/supervision Efficiency at Xu Lab, Carnegie Mellon University, 2022
- LLM pruning, Visual Informatics Group @ University of Texas at Austin, 2023
- The power of model sparsity, Multimedia Analytics (MA) Laboratory at City University of Hong Kong, 2024

## Conference Program Committee Member/Reviewer:

- NeurlPS, ICML, CVPR, UAI, DAC, SNN workshop. Reviewer.
- The European Conference on Machine Learning (ECML) [2020]. Session chair.

## SUPERVISION ACTIVITIES

#### **MSc Projects**

- Automated Object Recognition of Solar Panels in Aerial Photographs.
  Judith te Selle, Eindhoven University of Technology, 2022
- Aspect-based Few-shot Learning.

Phuong Trinh, Eindhoven University of Technology, 2022

- Impact of Parameter Sharing in Sparse Neural Networks. Pritham Raaj Kishore Anand, University of Aberdeen, 2024
- Adaptive Augmentation in Latent Space using Autoencoders.
  Nikhila Ramisett, University of Aberdeen, 2024

# Ph.D Project

Model Compression.
 Andi Li, University of Aberdeen, 2024

#### **BSc Projects**

 Exploring the Use of Hyperbolic Neural Networks within Class-Incremental Learning Ben Laurie, University of Aberdeen, 2024

# Intern Projects

- Parameter-Efficient LLM Fine Tuning
  Jengxiang Li, Dalian Ligong University, 2024
- Urban Understanding using Deep Learning
  Zheyan Qu, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications 2022
- LLM MoE Merging/Pruning Mingyu Cao, 2022

#### TEACHINGS

| Deep Learning (2AMM10), Eindhoven University of Technology       | 2020 |
|--|------|
| Deep Learning (2AMM10), Eindhoven University of Technology       | 2021 |
| Deep Learning (2AMM10), Eindhoven University of Technology       | 2023 |
| Applied Artificial Intelligence (CS5079), University of Aberdeen | 2024 |
| Data Mining and Deep Learning (CS552J), University of Aberdeen   | 2024 |

## RESEARCH & SELECTED PUBLICATION

Overall: **21** papers (8 **A\*** and 5 **A** conference paper, CORE Conference Ranking), 1 Jornal Paper 1 **Best Paper Award**, 1 **Best Paper Nomination Award**. (as of April 2024)

- Lu Yin, You Wu, .etc. Outlier Weighed Layerwise Sparsity (OWL): A Missing Secret Sauce for Pruning LLMs to High Sparsity. The Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2024
- Lu Yin, Ajay Jaiswal, .etc. Pruning Small Pre-Trained Weights Irreversibly and Monotonically Impairs "Difficult" Downstream Tasks in LLMs. The Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2024
- Jie Ji, Gen Li, **Lu Yin**, .etc. BiDST: Dynamic Sparse Training is a Bi-Level Optimization Problem. The Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**), 2024
- Lu Yin, Gen Li, Meng Fang, Li Shen, Tianjin Huang, Zhangyang Wang, Vlado Menkovski, Xiaolong Ma, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Shiwei Liu. *Dynamic Sparse Training Is also A Structure Sparsity Learner*. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2023
- Lu Yin, Shiwei Liu, Fang Meng, Tianjin Huang, Vlado Menkovski, Mykola Pechenizkiy. Lottery Pools: Winning More by Interpolating Tickets without Increasing Training or Inference Cost. Thirty-Seventh AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2023.
- Lu Yin, Vlado Menkovski, Meng Fang, Tianjin, Huang, Yulong Pei, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Decebal Constantin Mocanu, Shiwei Liu. Superposing Many Tickets into One: A Performance Booster for Sparse Neural Network Training. The 38th Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI). 2022.
- Shiwei Liu, **Lu Yin**, Decebal Constantin Mocanu, and Mykola Pechenizkiy. *Do We Actually Need Dense Over-Parameterization? In-Time Over-Parameterization in Sparse Training*. The Thirty-eighth International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**), PMLR, 2021.
- Tianjin Huang, **Lu Yin**, Zhenyu Zhang, Li Shen, Meng Fang, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Zhangyang Wang, Shiwei Liu. *Are Large Kernels Better Teachers than Transformers for ConvNets?* International Conference on Machine Learning (**ICML**), PMLR, 2023.

- Gen Li, Lu Yin, Jie Ji, Wei Niu, Minghai Qin, Bin Ren, Linke Guo, Shiwei Liu, Xiaolong Ma NeurRev: Train Better Sparse Neural Network Practically via Neuron Revitalization. The Twelfth International Conference on Learning Representations. (ICLR) 2024
- Shiwei Liu, Tianlong Chen, Xiaohan Chen, Zahra Atashgahi, Lu Yin, Huanyu Kou, Li Shen, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Zhangyang Wang, and Decebal Constantin Mocanu. Sparse Training via Boosting Pruning Plasticity with Neuroregeneration. The Thirty-fifth Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2021
- Zahra Atashgahi, Xuhao Zhang, Neil Kichler, Shiwei Liu, Lu Yin, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Raymond Veldhuis, Decebal Constantin Mocanu. Supervised Feature Selection with Neuron Evolution in Sparse Neural Networks. Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR).
- Tianjin Huang, Tianlong Chen, Meng Fang, Vlado Menkovski, Jiaxu Zhao, **Lu Yin**, Yulong Pei, Decebal Constantin Mocanu, Zhangyang Wang, Mykola Pechenizkiy, Shiwei Liu. *You Can Have Better Graph Neural Networks by Not Training Weights at All: Finding Untrained GNNs Tickets*. Learning on Graphs Conference (**LoG**). 2022. (**BEST PAPER AWARD**)
- Lu Yin, Vlado Menkovski, Mykola Pechenizkiy. Knowledge Elicitation using Deep Metric Learning and Psychometric Testing.
  The European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML-PKDD), Ghent, Belgium, 2020.
- Jiaxu Zhao\*, Lu Yin\*, Shiwei Liu, Fang Meng. Mykola Pechenizkiy. REST: Debiasing Deep Neural Networks through Reweighted Sparse Training. The European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML-PKDD). Turin, Italy, 2023. \*equal contribution
- Tianjin Huang, Shiwei Liu, Tianlong Chen, Meng Fang, Li Shen, Vlado Menkovski, Lu Yin, Yulong Pei, Mykola Pechenizkiy.
  Enhancing Adversarial Training via Reweighting Optimization Trajectory. The European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML-PKDD). Turin, Italy, 2023.
- Lu Yin. Beyond Labels: Knowledge Elicitation using Deep Metric Learning and Psychometric Testing. 29th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence-17th Pacific Rim International Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI DC), 2020. Doctoral Consortium.
- Lu Yin, Vlado Menkovski, Shiwei Liu, and Mykola Pechenizkiy. *Hierarchical Semantic Segmentation using Psychometric Learning*. The Thirteenth Asian Conference on Machine Learning (ACML), 2021. (LONG ORAL)
- Lu Yin, Vlado Menkovski, Yulong Pei, and Mykola Pechenizkiy. Semantic-Based Few-Shot Learning by Interactive Psychometric Testing. The Workshop on Interactive Machine Learning. The Thirty-Sixth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI Workshop), 2022
- Lu Yin, Vlado Menkovski, Yulong Pei, and Mykola Pechenizkiy. Semantic-Based Few-Shot Learning by Psychometric Testing. International Symposium on Intelligent Data Analysis (IDA). Springer, Cham, 2022.
- Fucheng Deng, Xiaorui Zhu, **Lu Yin**, Chao H, *Real-Time Detection of Polygons and Circles Based on Semantics*. 2018 IEEE International Conference on Information and Automation (ICIA). IEEE, 2018: 444-449.
- Xiaorui Zhu, Lu Yin, Fucheng Deng. Wind Disturbance Rejection in Position Control of Unmanned Helicopter by Nonlinear Damping. International Conference on Computer Vision Systems (ICVS). Springer, Cham, 2017: 590-599. (BEST PAPER NOMINEES AWARD)

More in: <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=G4Xe1NkAAAAJ">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=G4Xe1NkAAAAJ</a>